So today's דף daf is י yud and we pick up on
ט עמוד ב, tet amud bet, ריש לקיש הוה סחי, Reish Lakish
Hava Sachi, one two three four five six seven eight lines down
in the wide lines and we just had a whole interesting discussion
between רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish about why
like about the whole issue about ירידת הדורות Yeridat HaDorot about whether
earlier generations were greater or they weren't greater and connecting to the
question about why there's been no בנין בית המקדש Binyan Beit HaMikdash
in the you know why the first בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was
rebuilt after seventy years and the second בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and
then there has not yet been a rebuilding of the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash after the destruction of the second. So it's important to
keep that discussion
in mind as we now look at the following story. So let's
take a look. ריש לקיש הוה סחי בירדנא, Reish Lakish Hava Sachi
b'Yardena, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was bathing in the Jordan River. אתא
רבה בר בר חנה, Ata Rabbah bar Bar Chana, so רבה בר
בר חנה Rabbah bar Bar Chana a Babylonian אמורא Amora came who
was apparently in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for the time, we know
that the Babylonian אמוראים Amoraim spent time learning in ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. יהב ליה ידא Yehav lei yada and he stretched out his
hand to help ריש לקיש Reish Lakish out of the Jordan River.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said to him
as a thank you אלהא סני לכו, Eloha Sanei Lechu, your God
hates you. Okay, not a nice thing to say to somebody helping
you out of the river. דכתיב Dechtiv as the verse says אם
חומה היא נבנה עליה טירת כסף ואם דלת היא נצור עליה לוח
ארז. Im chomah hi nivneh aleha tirat kasef v'im delet hi natzur
aleha luach arez.
If she is a wall let us build upon her a tower
of silver and if she is a door let us build upon
her
a plank of cedar. So what does that mean? אם עשיתם עצמכם
כחומה ועליתם כולכם בימי עזרא. Im asitem atzmechem k'chomah v'alitem kulchem b'yimei
Ezra.
If you had made yourselves like a wall and had all come
up at the time of עזרא Ezra because most of the people
who were living in בבל Bavel the Jews stayed in בבל Bavel
after the time of
at the you know second בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Had you been
like a wall, what does it mean a wall? Like a wall's
one big unit, right? And if you'd all come up at the
time of עזרא, Ezra, נמשלתם ככסף שאין רקב שולט בו, Nimshaltem k'kasef
she'ein rakav sholeit bo, you would have been like silver that there
would have been no like rot that could set into you. עכשיו
שעליתם כדלתות, Achshav she'alitem k'dalatot,
now that you came up like doors. What does it mean like
doors? רש״י Rashi explains you know a door like you know it's
a little piece of the wall that opens and closes, it's not
the whole wall. So now that you've made yourself like a door
or רש״י Rashi says like you know if you have two doors
one opens one closes it's really something only very partial, now that
you made yourself like a door נמשלתם כארז שהרקב שולט בו, Nimshaltem
k'arez she'harakav sholeit bo, now you're like cedar
that rot you know can set into the wood. And now so
what does that mean? So it means thank you that the way
רש״י Rashi explains and the גמרא Gemorah is going to allude to
is that this is an explanation about why there has not been
a
בנין בית המקדש Binyan Beit HaMikdash why the second בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash was destroyed and hasn't been rebuilt. As I said that was
sort of like the background of the discussion if the later generations
are so great because of their תורה Torah so why is it
that the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash has not been rebuilt? So this
seems to be ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish answer to that question. You
know why? It's all the fault of the בני בבל Bnei Bavel
that they didn't come up in the time of עזרא Ezra and
now we're like ארז arez that הרקב שולט בו. harakav sholeit bo.
מאי ארז? Mai arez? What does it mean ארז? arez? What kind
of cedar? Wait let's take a look. מאי ארז? Mai arez? What
do you mean ארז? arez? אמר עולא ססמגור. Amar Ulla sasmagor. So
ססמגור sasmagor so which might just be the name of the Babylonian
name of cedar but רש״י Rashi also says that it basically refers
to a type of a worm a type that eats up on
the inside of the cedar wood so the inside gets rotted but
the outside is still around. מאי ססמגור? Mai sasmagor? And what's the
metaphor of that? אמר רבי אבא בת קול. Amar Rabbi Abba bat
kol. It means that while we don't have נבואה nevuah in the
second period in the time of the second בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
we don't have the fullness of God's presence but we have like
some external shell a בת קול. bat kol. כדתניא K'detanya משמתו נביאים
אחרונים חגי זכריה ומלאכי נסתלקה רוח הקודש מישראל ועדיין היו משתמשים בבת
קול. Mishemetu nevi'im acharonim Chaggai Zechariah u'Malachi nistalka Ruach HaKodesh m'Yisrael v'adayin
hayu mishtamshim b'bat kol. Once the old generation died out of the
נביאים nevi'im like the leftovers from the first בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
period חגי זכריה ומלאכי Chaggai Zechariah u'Malachi who were at the beginning
of the second בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, נסתלקה רוח הקודש מישראל, nistalka
Ruach HaKodesh m'Yisrael,
there was no longer any true divine presence the רוח הקודש. Ruach
HaKodesh. ועדיין היו משתמשים בבת קול, V'adayin hayu mishtamshim b'bat kol,
but they would still be some type of a presence of some
echo some בת קול bat kol some type of divine inspiration and
that's all that was left. Okay so this is what he's saying
if you want to know why second בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was
like at a lower level than the first, you know again maybe
it's more talking about the second בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and not
why there hasn't been a rebuilding of the third but still it
seems to be juxtaposed to the story we left off with yesterday.
It's not because we are of a lower level actually our תורה
Torah learning with the oppression is so much at a higher level
than the previous generations. There's other reasons. It's because that there you
know the lack of the fact that it was not a full
עליה aliyah that so many people remained in בבל. Bavel. There's other
sort of national reasons why we're at a different status. At least
the way I'm reading that as a response to the way the
discussion ended yesterday. Just one thing, the מהרש"א Maharsha makes a nice
point on reading the גמרא Gemara in light of the of ספר
עזרא, Sefer Ezra, the difference between a wall and a door and
he points out that at the beginning of the time of עזרא,
Ezra, if you read the פסוקים, Pesukim, they needed to be they
needed to be guarding the walls because of the attacks from the
surrounding people that did not want them for Samaritans and others did
not want them building the second בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So he
says if so many of you had come up, but you would
have served like a wall, there would have been so many of
us we wouldn't have needed the protections of the walls, then it
would have been a very different story. But now he says you
came up only in sort of like doors, there were only enough
of you like as it were to guard the doors, there was
not so many that really served as a true protection. So he
connects it to those to that actual historical event of the time
of עזרא. Ezra. Yes Charlie.
According to these three oaths, we're not supposed to ascend like a
wall.
That's after the חורבן Churban of the בית שני. Bayis Sheini. There's
a lot of things...
No, but he's saying the reason why things weren't aren't so good,
weren't so good from the בית שני Bayis Sheini on is because
of that you didn't the way you didn't return in בית שני.
Bayis Sheini. The גמרא Gemara that speaks in כתובות Kesubos about שלא
shelo שבועה shevuah not to be עולה בחומה oleh b'choma which is
the exact same metaphor here, it's talking about from after בית שני
Bayis Sheini regarding בית שלישי, Bayis Shlishi, so it's a different story.
These oaths emerged because of these failures. Right. Yes. What's this notion
of בת קול? Bas Kol? Yeah, I always wondered what that was,
but in this context it's not even a voice, it's like the
daughter of a voice, or the shadow.
Right, that's why I sort of said like he echoed, the echo
right, translate it as the echo, right. It's not the actual רוח
הקודש, Ruach Hakodesh, right, it's just some type of a distant echo.
Okay, I mean I think Lieberman points out, Saul Lieberman points out
that בת קול Bas Kol in the בבלי Bavli very much is
about like this sort of distant heavenly voice whereas in the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi I think if I remember correctly he says it does not
have any metaphysical connotations. It means like if a בת קול Bas
Kol went out it means like a report came out, meaning like
the word spread about something, or a consensus emerged about something, it
doesn't actually suggest some type of a divine force. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, another question?
Yes. How can then someone for instance say רש"י Rashi had רוח
הקודש Ruach Hakodesh when this clearly says...
you'll have to ask the people that say that. Okay, כי דאתא,
ki d'ata, oh we just did that. ריש לקיש מי משתעי Reish
Lakish mi mishata בהדי רבה בר בר חנה? b'haday Rabba bar bar
Chana?
Now, we would read this story and we would say here's poor
רבה בר בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chana helping him out of
the river and he's just attacking him. So the גמרא Gemara has
a different question. Why would he even bother speaking to רבה בר
בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chana or would he even speak to
רבה בר בר חנה? Rabba bar bar Chana?
ומה רבי אלעזר דמרי דארעא דישראל הוה, U'ma Rebbi Elazar d'marei d'artza
d'Yisroel hava, רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar who was like considered the master
of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisroel, I mean that's a phrase in another
גמרא Gemara tells that story about why he has that name but
he was such an important personage, ולא הוה משתעי ריש לקיש בהדיה,
v'lo hava mishata Reish Lakish badei, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would not
speak with him. Why? דמאן דמשתעי ריש לקיש בהדיה בשוקא, D'man d'mishata
Reish Lakish badei beshuka, whoever ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would speak to
in public, יהבו ליה עיסקא בלא סהדי, yavlu lei iska b'lo sa'adi,
people would do business with such a person without witnesses, meaning if
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would speak to him, he's completely beyond reproach,
completely trustworthy, and therefore they would be willing to do business with
him without getting any signatures, without getting any witnesses. So ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish would be extremely careful who he would speak to because
of the way that would send the messages that would send to
the people in the community. So if that's true the גמרא Gemara
assumes that רבה בר בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chana certainly wasn't
at the level of רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar and if ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish wasn't going to speak to רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar he
wouldn't speak to רבה בר בר חנה. Rabba bar bar Chana.
So בהדי רבה בר בר חנה משתעי, b'haday Rabba bar bar Chana
mishata, he would talk with רבה בר בר חנה? Rabba bar bar
Chana? So אמר רב פפא שדי גברא בינייהו. Amar Rav Pappa shadi
gavra beinaihu. Okay, you have to exchange one of the people. או
ריש לקיש הוה וזעירי, O Reish Lakish hava v'Zeiri, either it was
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish who was
swimming and it was the person that helped him out of the
river was זעירי, Zeiri, I'm sorry did I mean that right?
Yeah, או ריש לקיש הוה וזעירי, o Reish Lakish hava v'Zeiri, it
was זעירי Zeiri who helped out ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, right, okay,
או רבה בר בר חנה הוה, o Rabba bar bar Chana hava,
or it was רבה בר בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chana who
stretched out the hand ורבי אלעזר v'Rebbi Elazar and it was רבי
אלעזר Rebbi Elazar who was swimming in the river. Okay, so you
have to do something so the story can make sense. Okay, כי
אתו לקמיה דרבי יוחנן, Ki azlu l'kamei d'Rabbi Yochanan, now when they
came to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, which by the way makes it
very seem to be that it was therefore ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
who the story was about because the relationship
between רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש...
Reish Lakish... yeah, that's true. So now they came to רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan
and
told him so
anyway רש"י Rashi says it means ריש לקיש Reish Lakish came to
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and told him the story, you know it
would make a little bit more sense if the person that got
this response from ריש לקיש Reish Lakish told רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
the story, anyway אמר ליה לאו היינו טעמא, amar lei lav hai
hu ta'ama, that's not the reason, the reason why it's not at
the same מדריגה madreiga בית שני... Bayis Sheini... for בית ראשון Bayit
Rishon is not because there was not a big, like a huge
עליה. aliyah. אי נמי סליקו כולהו בימי עזרא, ee nami seliku kulhu
b'yemei Ezra, even
if all of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael had come up in the
time of עזרא, Ezra, לא הוי שריא שכינה במקדש שני, lo havi
sharya Shchina b'mikdash sheni, there would not have been the presence of
the שכינה Shchina in the second בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Why? דכתיב,
dichsiv, because the פסוק pasuk says, יפת אלוהים ליפת וישכון באהלי שם,
Yaft Elokim l'Yefet v'yishkon b'ahalei Shem, always a good פסוק pasuk to
be talking about around חנוכה Chanukah time. Okay, God will expand יפת,
Yefet, but he will dwell in the tents of שם. Shem. Okay,
so this was obviously the ברכה bracha that נח Noach gave to
his children. So the גמרא Gemara reads this classically, אף על גב
דיפת אלוהים ליפת, af al gav d'yaft Elokim l'Yefet,
although God will expand יפת Yefet and also יפת yaft here means
to beautify יפת, Yefet, okay, and often that's read as the, anyway,
אין השכינה שורה אלא באוהלי שם. ein haShchina shora ella b'ahalei Shem.
So meaning although the בית המקדש השני, Beis HaMikdash HaSheni, which was
constructed, now it really wasn't made by the Greeks, although that's what
the גמרא's Gemara going to ask, it was given, they were allowed
to return because of כורש Koresh who was a Persian, but the
גמרא Gemara will discuss this, try to argue in a minute that
the Persians are descendant from יפת. Yefet.
So although that is expansive, although in a way it's more beautiful,
the בית שני Bayis Sheni was actually, although when they first built
it you read in עזרא Ezra everybody was crying because it wasn't
as beautiful as the first בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but by the
time you got to הורדוס Herod and the expansion of it, it
was even bigger and more beautiful. Even if all of that is
true, God's ultimately the presence is באוהלי שם, b'ahalei Shem, only in
the tents that come from שם, Shem, meaning only in the בית
המקדש הראשון Beis HaMikdash HaRishon which was built by, you know, by
שלמה, Shlomo, which was built by descendants of שם. Shem. So yes,
the בית המקדש השני Beis HaMikdash HaSheni was beautiful but it wasn't
a purely Jewish temple, you know, if you want you could say
it's not just who the builder was but it wasn't done by
us when we were, had our own, you know, autonomous government and
when we had ourselves dominion, it was done under the subjugation of
other nations and therefore the presence of God is also diminished as
well. Now that's interesting to read because a classic מדרש Midrash on
יפת אלוהים ליפת Yaft Elokim l'Yefet is יפיותו של יפת באוהלי שם,
yafyuso shel Yefet b'ahalei Shem, that it's not sort of setting it
as a dichotomy but actually bringing them together. The beauty of יפת
Yefet can come together as in the tents of שם, Shem, and
speaking about a merging of those two. Here it's being read as
a dichotomy. Yes, Charlie?
They don't mention Herod rebuilding the temple and Herod was a descendant
of...
Right. Well, exactly. Okay. I know. So it's, so we're talking about
the first, I mean about the first rebuilding as well. I threw
in Herod for the historical context. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ופרסאי מנלן דמיפת קאתו, u'Parsayei minalan d'miYefet ka'asu, since when do the
Persians, because that's it was rebuilt under the Persians, since when do
they come from יפת? Yefet? דכתיב בני יפת גומר ומגוג ומדי ויון
ותובל ומשך ותירס. dichsiv bnei Yefet Gomer u'Magog u'Madai v'Yavan v'Tuval u'Meshech
v'Tiras. And now we're going to explain what each of these places
is. So גומר זה גרממיא, Gomer ze Garmamya, גומר Gomer is גרממיא,
Garmamya, which makes you want to say Germany, but it's doubtful that
the גמרא Gemara would have identified that with the sons of יפת.
Yefet. I have no idea if anybody has an English that gives
any reasonable translation. Artscroll has a map? Okay. Wonderful. What, what do
they identify it with? Like what ancient nation? I'm asking what... I
don't have it.
Nobody else has a...
I got, yeah. What's... גרממיא? Garmamya?
גרממיא Garmamya is Germany.
They want to say it means Germany? Well, okay. First of all,
there's a question whether if you look, the גר״א Gra says it's
גרמניא. Germanya. Our גירסא girsa is גרממיא. Garmamya. I'm doubtful that it
really...
Steinsaltz identifies it with a region north of Assyria, Phrygia, I think.
Okay. And there was something there that had a name like that?
Armenia? I think that's probably much more reasonable. Okay. Because these are
the places, these places are not in, you know, Western Europe. מגוג
זה קנדיא. Magog ze Kandya. So that's Canada. Okay. If גרממיא Garmamya
is Germany then מגוג Magog is Canada. Magog is... I don't know,
I
just, I should have brought...
Ours identifies it as Scythia or Crete. Crete? That makes... or Mongolia.
Mongolia probably more than Crete. Again, the more Western it is, the
more doubtful it is. What does the Steinsaltz say? Scythia.
And then there's a גירסא girsa of גותיא, Gothya, which is Goth,
in
Asia Minor.
Asia Minor? Or the Goths.
Goths. They were German. Okay. But it doesn't have to be Jews,
they just had to be aware of it.
ומדי זה מקדוניא. u'Madai ze Makdonya. So מדי Madai is Macedonia. That
is Greece actually. יון
כמשמעו. Yavan k'mashmao. So יון Yavan is Greece. So how is Greece
and Macedonia different? Weren't, wasn't Greece and Macedonia...?
No, Macedonia's a different ethnic environment north. Alexander was Macedonian.
Okay. Okay. So I guess we are getting more into Western Europe.
תובל זה בית אונייקי. Tuval ze Beis Onaiki. תובל Tuval is בית
אונייקי. Beis Onaiki. Anybody?
Bithynia. I don't know what that means. Northwest Asia Minor.
Okay. Dov, what do you got there? Same thing. Okay. משך זו
מוסיא. Meshech zu Mosya. משך Meshech is מוסיא. Mosya. Anybody? Northwest
Bithynia. Northwest... Oh, now we got it.
Along the Sea of Marmara and the Dardanelles.
All right. תירס, Tiras, תירס Tiras is corn. No, תירס. Tiras. פליגי
בר סימאי ורבנן ואמרי לה רבי סימון ורבנן. pleigei bar Simai ve-Rabanan
ve-amrei lah Rabi Simon ve-Rabanan. חד אמר זה בית תרייקי, chad amar
zeh Beit Taryaiki,
which I assume they say is
Turkey? No? Thrace? Oh, that makes more sense. Thrace makes more sense.
That's in the Greek area, Greece area, right? Yeah. וחד אמר זו
פרס, ve-chad amar zu Pras, and the other says it's Persia. Okay.
So we did all this to get to the opinion that it's
Persia. So this also רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan that said that it
was because of the dichotomy between בית ראשון Bayis Rishon בית שני,
Bayis Sheni, יפת אלהים ליפת Yaft Elokim le-Yafet versus עולי בבל, olei
Bavel, would understand that Persia was descended from יון. Yavan. תני tani
we taught in a ברייתא. braita.
I think every one of these people spoke an Indo-European language. Oh,
so
which would be our argument for יפת. Yafet.
Oh, interesting. In terms of the language that's all
linked together, mostly.
Yeah. I probably shouldn't have been pushing back so much on the
question about western and eastern Europe because, you know,
because clearly some of the ones that are in the area of
Greece are in the western Europe. But I still doubt that גרממיא,
Germamya, I mean the הגר"א ha-Gra switches it to גרממיא. Germamya. But
anyway, it's a Roman word. Anyway, okay. Anyway, רבנן, Rabanan, okay. So
anyway, so anyway, that's how you get this idea of פרס. Pras.
תני רב יוסף, tani Rav Yosef, תירס זו פרס. Tiras zu Pras.
Now we finish the פסוק. pasuk. סבתא ורעמה וסבתכא, Sabta ve-Raamah ve-Sabtecha,
I think is at the end of it, right? So סבתא, Sabta,
oh, סבתא ורעמה וסבתכא, Sabta ve-Raamah ve-Sabtecha, excuse me. So
סבתא ורעמה וסבתכא. Sabta ve-Raamah ve-Sabtecha. That's the end of the פסוק
pasuk after the listing of
תירס. Tiras. סבתא ורעמה וסבתכא. Sabta ve-Raamah ve-Sabtecha. תני רב יוסף, tani
Rav Yosef, so סבתא Sabta is סקיסתאן, Skistan, wherever that is, סקיסתאן
גוייתא, Skistan Gavyata, the outer
סקיסתאן, Skistan, וסקיסתאן ברייתא, ve-Skistan Brayta, and וסבתכא, ve-Sabtecha, which sounds like
the word סבתא, Sabta, is the inner סקיסתאן. Skistan. Any explanation of
what סקיסתאן Skistan is? Sakastan. What? Sakastan.
Sakastene. What?
Okay. Drangiana, an area spanning west Afghanistan and east Iran. Okie doke.
So the הגר"א ha-Gra fine.
All right, moving on. So anyway, so there's an outer and an
inner one, so he imagines it as two rings, an outer ring
and then an inner like circle of the inner part of the
inner, the סבתא Sabta and the סבתכא. Sabtecha. So בין חדא לחדא
מאה פרסי, bein chada le-chada mea parsi, so the distance, you know,
the gap between the outer ring and the inner ring, the space
between them is a hundred פרסי, parsi, which is about a mile.
בני כוש Benei Kush by the way these people.
Oh, I'm sorry, they're בני כוש, Benei Kush, not בני יפת. Benei
Yafet. Thank you. Read the פסוק pasuk there, בני כוש: Benei Kush:
סבא וחוילה. Seba ve-Havilah. Right after the פסוק pasuk of בני יון.
Benei Yavan.
סבתא ורעמה וסבתכא, Sabta ve-Raamah ve-Sabtecha, ובני רעמה שבא ודדן. u-venei Raamah
Sheba ve-Dedan.
Ah, okay, fine. יישר כח. shkoach. Thank you. Okay, so this is
no longer בני יון, Benei Yavan, this is בני כוש. Benei Kush.
Which is חם, Cham,
which is חם, Cham, right. So thank you. Okay, so there's a
hundred פרסי, parsi, whatever miles, between the outer ring and the inner
circle.
מאה פרסי, mea parsi, והיקפה אלפא פרסי, ve-heikefah alfa parsi, and the
circumference of presumably the outer circle is a hundred פרסי, parsi, so
you can do the math. Thousand, excuse me, a thousand, you can
do the math. ותהי ראשית ממלכתו בבל. va-tehi reishit mamlachto Bavel. Now
that we're talking about all this, let's talk about נמרוד, Nimrod, who
is the one personality that emerges from all of this story of
the generation of, you know, the various descendants of נח. Noach.
So בני כוש, Benei Kush, so these are כוש Kush had סבא,
Seba, חוילה Havilah and all these other people. Right. And then כוש
Kush also had נמרוד. Nimrod.
Right. Right. So now we're continuing in the פסוקים. pesukim. Right. So
we had יון, Yavan, then we mentioned something. Right. I mean, Micah's
probably right what we're probably also doing is looking at this whole
section of פרשת נח Parshat Noach and mentioning like, you know, interesting
rabbinic statements about it. So we started with the בני יון Benei
Yavan to get to this issue about Persia, and now we're mentioning
other comments so we're moving down, so after יון Yavan you have
כוש, Kush, and then you have נמרוד. Nimrod. ותהי ראשית ממלכתו בבל,
va-tehi reishit mamlachto Bavel, the beginning of his ruling was, or kingship
was in בבל, Bavel, וארך ואכד וכלנה, ve-Erech ve-Akad ve-Calneh, and ארך
Erech and אכד Akad and כלנה. Calneh. So what are these places?
בבל כמשמעו, Bavel kemashmao, Babylonia. ארך, Erech, זה אוריכות. zeh Orichot. I
don't know what does אוריכות Orichot mean. Anybody?
Uruk.
Uruk? Yeah, the archeologists found it 150 years ago.
Okay. Where is that located?
It was a huge city in what is now Iraq.
Okay. So, okay. ואכד, ve-Akad, now אכד Akad is Acadia, right?
I mean they had... So anyway, the גמרא Gemara here says זה
בשכר, zeh Bashkar, which is I don't know if that's just another
word they had for Acadia or something else.
Actually, Artscroll says it's Akkad. What? Yeah, Artscroll says it's Akkad.
Yeah, but I bet the גמרא Gemara says it's בשכר, Bashkar, so...
well, the Artscroll's down...
I don't know. כלנה, Calneh, now כלנה, Calneh, זה נופר נינפי. zeh
Nofar Ninphi. Okay, whatever that is. מן הארץ ההיא יצא אשור, min
ha-aretz ha-hi yatza Ashur, from that land אשור Ashur came out. So
תני רב יוסף, tani Rav Yosef, אשור זה סילק. Ashur zeh Silak.
Assyria is סילק. Silak. I don't know what this סילק Silak is.
What does it say for סילק? Silak? Assyria.
It
says
Seleucia.
Seleucid? Seleucid.
Alexander divided his empire into three.
Right.
Seleucids and I forget the third.
Antigonids.
Right, that's the Chanukah, the Seleucids is is right is is about...
okay. It's in Iraq. Mid second century before the common era.
So what's the identification of the Seleucids? It's a subsection of Alexander
the Greek's kingdom.
Alexander divided the kingdom
between three generals:
Syria, Mesopotamia, Iran, and India. And Iran and India very quickly broke
away.
I see, I see. Okay. Alright, very appropriate for Chanukah. ויבן
את נינוה, Vayiven et Ninveh, he built Ninveh. ואת רחובות עיר ואת
כלח, ve'et Rechovot Ir ve'et Kalach, and Rechovot Ir and Kalach. נינוה
כמשמעו, Ninveh kema'shmao, Ninveh is Ninveh. We know the famous city of
Ninveh. רחובות עיר זו פרת. Rechovot Ir zu Perat. Rechovot Ir is
the Euphrates. I mean, I only knew the Euphrates as a river,
but maybe there was a city Euphrates or a region. פרת דמישן,
Perat de'Meshan, the Perat of Meshan. כלח זו פרת דבורסי,
Kalach zu Perat de'Borsi, and Kalach is Perat of Borsi, presumably means
different areas on the Euphrates. Okay, ואת רסן, ve'et Resen, and of
course it seems like it's talking about cities, but okay, cities at
different locations. Passaic, there you go. ואת רסן בין נינוה ובין כלח
היא העיר הגדולה, ve'et Resen bein Ninveh uvein Kalach hi ha'ir hagedolah,
and Resen which is between Ninveh and Kalach, that is the big
city. So Resen, זו אקטיספון. zu Aktispon. Oh wow, Aktispon. What's wow?
That was the Persian capital.
Oh it was? Aktispon? Yeah, okay. היא
העיר הגדולה. hi ha'ir hagedolah. איני יודע. eini yodea. So which is
the big city? אם נינוה העיר הגדולה אם רסן העיר הגדולה. im
Ninveh ha'ir hagedolah im Resen ha'ir hagedolah. Which one? It says ואת
רסן בין נינוה ובין כלח היא העיר הגדולה. ve'et Resen bein Ninveh
uvein Kalach hi ha'ir hagedolah. Now of course the Maharsha says, what
about Kalach? It sounds Kalach היא העיר הגדולה. hi ha'ir hagedolah. He
says no, if Kalach was the big city, it would have said
ואת כלח העיר הגדולה. ve'et Kalach ha'ir hagedolah. היא העיר הגדולה hi
ha'ir hagedolah seems to be referring to one of the previous ones.
So which one is it? Is it Ninveh or is it Resen?
So the Gemara says אם נינוה העיר הגדולה אם רסן העיר הגדולה.
im Ninveh ha'ir hagedolah im Resen ha'ir hagedolah. כשהוא אומר keshehu omer
ונינוה ve'Ninveh when it says a little bit later in Tanakh, Yonah,
ונינוה הייתה עיר גדולה לאלהים מהלך שלושת ימים, ve'Ninveh hayetah ir gedolah
l'Elohim mahalach sheloshet yamim, הוי אומר נינוה היא העיר הגדולה. hevei omer
Ninveh hi ha'ir hagedolah. Of course, the size of cities might have
changed between Breishit and Yonah, fine. Okay, and anyway it's also relative
to Resen, so you don't know which is Resen. Ninveh could be
big and Resen could be big. Anyway. Okay, ושם אחימן ששי ותלמי.
vesham Achiman Sheshai veTalmai. Now that we're talking about bigness, and we're
also talking about trying to like name sort of people and places
or places, we jump a little bit ahead to Bamidbar. There was
אחימן ששי ותלמי. Achiman Sheshai veTalmai. There when the scouts scattered out
the land of Canaan, there were these three people, ילידי הענק, yelidei
ha'anak, sons of the giant. So תנא, tana, אחימן, Achiman, מיומן שבאחין.
meyuman shebe'achin. What is Achiman? Like from the word ימין, yamin, the
right, the largest, the strongest of the brothers. ששי, Sheshai, so what
is Sheshai? שמשים את הארץ כשחיתות. she'mesim et ha'aretz keshchitut. He makes
the land like, you know, like destruction,
so he lays waste to the land. So again, exactly where that's
from, the Sheshai, שחיתות, shchitut, maybe ששי שמשים, Sheshai she'mesim, although the
Gemara is going to use the word שמשים she'mesim in a minute,
but he's so large, you know, he sort of he tramples on
the land and he destroys it. תלמי, Talmai, what's Talmai? שמשים את
הארץ תלמים תלמים. she'mesim et ha'aretz telamim telamim. There you see more
how it's reading the word. When he walks on the land, he
makes it into furrows, like, you know, he's so big that it
causes the land to crack wherever he walks. דבר אחר, davar acher,
אחימן, Achiman, בנה
ענת. bana Anat. So Achiman built the city of Anat. A little
question why it's דבר אחר davar acher and it no longer seems
to be connecting to the names, just making, you know, sort of
historical statements. Achiman built the city of Anat, ששי בנה אלוש. Sheshai
bana Alush. Where's Anat?
I have no idea. Sheshai built Alush. I mean we know where
Alush is, right? Charlie, where's Alush? Okay, I don't know. Anyway, תלמי
בנה תלבוש. Talmai bana Talbosh. Okay, now ילידי ענק, yelidei anak,
so the children of the of Anak, so literally the giants, שמעניקים
החמה בקומתן. she'ma'anikim hachamah bekumatan. They, from the word, they basically the
way Rashi explains is an ענק anak can also be like a
necklace. They make the necklace, you know, they make the sun into
a necklace, they're so big. They stand up so tall, you know,
you look at it and like it looks like the sun is
going around their neck, something like that. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי
אמר רבי, amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi amar Rabbi, עתידה רומי שתפול
ביד
פרת. atidah Romi shetipol beyad Perat. Now eventually, right, Rome was obviously
the current government and you know like we just had the whole
thing about about the dream of Yaakov and the ladder and the
famous Midrash is that the angels were the, you know, vision about
the different, you know, about the different kingdoms that ruled over the
Jewish people, you know, and he sees, you know, and he sees
פרת Perat and he sees יון Yavan going up and down and
then he sees Rome going up and not coming down, you know,
and he sort of says like you know when when will the
dominion of Rome ever end? So you have to understand that from
Chazal's perspective, right, it looked like there was no end to it.
Rome was this supremely... powerful government, kingdom, and so when is it
ever going to end? When are we ever going to be free
from this subjection?
The Persians were still powerful at that time.
At that time? No, no.
Oh yeah, they were? Okay. They were under Persian rule. Yeah, yeah.
Wait, wait, wait.
No, no, no.
בבלי Bavli was written under Persian rule.
I understand.
But were they like a powerful Sassanian?
Yes, they were very powerful.
Aha. Against Rome. Against Rome. They were a theoretical threat to Rome.
They were not a theoretical, they were a real threat on
the eastern border, the eastern
border of the Roman Empire. In fact, in the early 7th century,
they conquered the entire Middle East from the Romans.
Really?
And then they lost it.
Okay. Which century? 7th? Beginning of 7th century.
All right. All right. So עתידה רומי שתפול ביד פרס. Atida Romi
shetipol beyad Pras. Who in the end, I mean, I know that
like, you know, Rome, I always see like, right, you know, as
like overrun with barbarians, the sacking of Rome, but what nation actually
was it? The Mongols? What nation actually? The Goths. The Goths.
And then the Vandals.
And they were Northern what we would call
Northern Germany.
They were
Germans.
Germanic tribes, right? Yes, Germanic tribes. Okay. All right. So אמר רבי,
Amar Rebbe, עתידה רומי שתפול ביד פרס. Atida Romi shetipol beyad Pras.
So they are looking towards a future time when maybe, you know,
the Roman kingdom will fall and presumably also then the Jews will
be free from subjection. You understand by the way that what happens
in חז״ל Chazal since we're reading the whole יעקב עשו Yaakov Esav
stories is that, you know, עשו Esav in the תורה Torah is
like the competitor with יעקב Yaakov and also like לאום ולאום יאמץ,
leom uleom yeematz, one goes up, the other goes down. So חז״ל,
Chazal, now עשו Esav in the תורה Torah represents אדום, Edom, but
אדום Edom is a nation that disappeared in biblical times. חז״ל, Chazal,
you know, basically, not necessarily was conscious, but found a substitute, you
know, had to sort of apply אדום Edom to its reality. אדום
Edom became Rome because Rome was the subjugator of, you know, of
the Jewish people. And then of course when Rome fell, אדום Edom
became Christianity. Now that was possible because of the whole Holy Roman
Empire, but it's important to understand how that transference, right, of becomes
from עשו Esav to אדום, Edom, אדום Edom to Rome, and Rome
to Christianity.
The גמרא Gemara
just takes it for granted.
The Holy Roman Empire was hundreds of years after this.
I understand, but I'm saying why how is it that in how
is it that in the Middle Ages אדום Edom is Christianity, right?
It's because of that transference. Okay, anyway, so עתידה רומי שתפול ביד
פרס, Atida Romi shetipol beyad Pras, eventually Rome will fall in the
hands of the Persians. שנאמר, Sheneemar, the Roman Empire. שנאמר, Sheneemar, as
it says,
לכן שמעו עצת ה׳ אשר יעץ אל אדום ומחשבותיו אשר חשב אל
ישבי תימן אם לא יסחבום צעירי הצאן, Lachen shim'u atzat Hashem asher
ya'atz el Edom umachshovotav asher chashav el yoshvei Teiman. Im lo yis'chavum
tze'irei hatzon, the young of the sheep will sweep them away. So
the young of the sheep is understood to be פרס. Pras. אם
לא ישים עליהם נוהם, Im lo yashim aleihem noham, if they will
not place upon them like a, you know, a bellowing. So מתקיף
לה רבא בר עולא מאי משמע דהאי צעירי הצאן פרס? Matkif lah
Rava bar Ulla, mai mashma dehai tze'irei hatzon Pras? How do you
know that the young of the sheep means Persia? דכתיב Dechtiv because
it says in the vision in דניאל, Daniel, האיל אשר ראית בעל
הקרנים מלכי מדי ופרס. ha'ayil asher ra'ita ba'al hakarnayim malchei Madai uPharas.
The ram that you saw, right, this was the vision of נבוכדנצר,
Nevuchadnezzar, the ram that you saw
that had all that had the horns, those are the kings of
Media and Persia. So you see that צאן, tzon, sheep, and ram,
ram is is פרס. Pras. Okay. ואימא יון? Ve'eima Yavan? So what
why associate it with that? How about to have maybe it's Greek,
Greece? דכתיב Dechtiv because then he says, וצפיר השעיר מלך יון. utzfir
hasayir melech Yavan. And the goat, the he-goat
is the king of יון. Yavan. So צאן tzon could also include
goats, maybe it's maybe it's Greece. What makes you identify it with
Persia? כי סליק רב חביבא בר סורמקי, Ki salik Rav Chaviva bar
Surmaki, when רב חביבא בר סורמקי Rav Chaviva bar Surmaki went up
to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר קמי דהוא מרבנן. amar kammai dahu
meirabbanan. He said this discussion in front of one of the רבנן,
rabbanan, you know, this teaching that it was that it was פרס,
Pras, but the question of exactly how we knew that, and אמר
ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, מאן דלא ידע פירושא
דקרא מוציא תיופתא. man delo yada perusha dikra motzi tiyufta. A person
who doesn't know how to interpret the פסוקים pesukim asks questions. It
was a question out of ignorance. You assumed that the reason צאן
tzon was identified was a פסוק pasuk in דניאל Daniel and therefore
you asked your question. The problem is you didn't understand what he
was really doing by identifying צאן tzon as פרס. Pras. Why?
מאי תיופתא לרבי? Mai tiyufta leRebbe? Challenges רבי. Rebbe. So מאי צעירי
הצאן? mai tze'irei hatzon? What is צעירי הצאן? tze'irei hatzon? זוטרא דאחוהי.
Zutra d'achavahi. It means the youngest of the brothers and we said
before that the youngest of of בני יפת bnei Yefet which תירס
Tiras was the youngest was פרס. Pras. So of course it's not
clear so how do you know even if the צעיר tze'ir means
the youngest, like the small of the flock, we're not doing a
metaphor, the flock and sheep represents Persia. The metaphor is the youngest
of the flock. So who's the youngest of the flock? The youngest
of the children of of יפת Yefet which is תירס, Tiras, which
is פרס. Pras. Of course
the... Anyway that's the explanation. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. דתני רב יוסף De-tani Rav Yosef תירס זו
פרס. Tiras zu Pras. אמר רבה בר בר חנה Amar Rabbah bar
bar Chana אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan משום רבי יהודה ברבי
אלעאי, mishum Rabbi Yehuda be-Rabbi Ilai, עתידה רומי שתפול ביד פרס. atida
Romi she-tipol be-yad Pras. Now we're going to make the same statement:
in the end Rome will fall in the hands of Persia. קל
וחומר. Kal VaChomer. I like the קל וחומר. Kal VaChomer. Okay, we
know history follows קל וחומר. Kal VaChomers. ומה מקדש ראשון שבנוהו בני
שם, U-mah Mikdash Rishon she-benuhu Bnei Shem, the first temple goes off
the back of this idea of אהלי שם Oholei Shem versus, you
know, יפת, Yefet, the first בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was built by
the descendants of שם, Shem, was built by שלמה, Shlomo, והחריבוהו כשדיים
ve-hecherivuhu Kasdim and the Kasdim, you know, destroyed it, נפלו כשדיים ביד
פרסיים naflu Kasdim be-yad Parsiyim and then the Kasdim fell under the,
you know, that kingship, that empire fell to the Persians. מקדש שני
שבנוהו פרסיים, Mikdash Sheni she-benuhu Parsiyim, so the second בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash that was built by the Persians, meaning it was built under
the auspices of כורש, Koresh, והחריבוהו רומיים ve-hecherivuhu Romiyim and the Romans
destroyed it, אינו דין שיפלו רומיים ביד פרסיים? eino din she-yipelu Romiyim
be-yad Parsiyim? How much more so would the Romans fall in the
hands of the Persians? Now even from a קל וחומר Kal VaChomer
argument this is weak. Forget the fact that history doesn't conform. Right,
this is sort of like you'd see, it seems like the transitive
axiom of inequality. Right, so the Persians beat out the Kasdim and
then the Romans beat out the Persians, so how do you think
the Persians are going to beat out the Romans?
Obviously the קל וחומר, Kal VaChomer,
no, the קל וחומר Kal VaChomer is the Persians, if the Persians
were able to destroy something created by, you know, by בני ישראל,
Bnei Yisrael, by בני שם, Bnei Shem, which obviously should have been
the last מקדש, Mikdash, how much more will the Persians be able
to destroy something that was, you know, the people that could wipe
out the second בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. I don't even really get
the קל וחומר. Kal VaChomer. Anyway, so אמר, amar, so that's this
קל וחומר. Kal VaChomer.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רב, Amar Rav, said רב, Rav, עתידה פרס שתפול ביד רומי.
atida Pras she-tipol be-yad Romi. You got it wrong, he said. It's
not that Rome will fall under Persia, פרס Pras will eventually be
conquered by
Rome. אמרו ליה רב כהנא ורב אסי לרב, Amru leh Rav Kahana
ve-Rav Assi le-Rav, בנויי ביד סתורי? banuyei be-yad saturei? How is that
possible? פרס Pras are the good guys, right? So we were basically
assuming the good guys, פרס, Pras, who allowed the second בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash to be rebuilt, they would destroy Rome. You're saying the
Romans who destroyed it will destroy פרס? Pras? How could that be?
They're the good guys. So the בנויי, banuyei, the builders, will fall
in the hands of the סתורי, saturei, the destroyers? אמר להו, Amar
le-hu, אין, in, yes, גזירת המלך היא. gezerat ha-melech hi. That's God's
will. That's the way history works. Okay, Rome is supreme and they're
going to wipe out פרס Pras even if פרס Pras were the
good guys. So איכא דאמרי, ika de-amri, some say אמר, amar, אינהו
נמי קא סתרי בי כנישתא. inhu nami ka satrei bei knishta. Don't
think פרס Pras are always only good guys. They also קא סתרי
בי כנישתא, ka satrei bei knishta, they also wipe out synagogues, which
is interesting because we know that, you know, the Jews had it
very good under Persian rule and they had it very good in
בבל, Bavel, so it's not exactly clear what historical context he's referring
to. But the point is, פרס Pras aren't such good guys either.
Still, Rome were worse. Anyway, תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, we
taught similarly, עתידה פרס שתפול ביד רומי. atida Pras she-tipol be-yad Romi.
פרס Pras will fall into the hands of Rome. חדא, chada,
number one, דסתרי בי כנישתא, de-satrei bei knishta, they destroy synagogues and
therefore they deserve, why that proves that they'll fall in the hands
of Rome I don't know, but they're not total good guys. ועוד
גזירת המלך היא שיפלו בוני ביד סותרי. ve-od gezerat ha-melech hi she-yipelu
bonei be-yad sotrei. Anyway, it's God's desire. Yes, sometimes the builders will
fall in the hand of the destroyers. I mean, let's face it,
the destroyers are good at destroying. So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב,
amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, אין בן דוד בא, ein Ben David
ba, the son of David, the משיח Mashiach won't come עד שתפשוט
מלכות רומי הרשעה בכל העולם כולו, ad she-tifshot malchut Romi ha-resha'ah be-chol
ha-olam kulo, until the evil Roman kingdom will have dominion over the
entire world. So you're, you're saying, you know, you're imagining there's going
to be an immediate counterbalance. Rome was supreme, they've got, they've now
got to be destroyed. He's like a more pessimistic view. No, they're
going to take over the entire world and only then, when things
are the most desperate, that's when משיח Mashiach is going to come.
Exactly. תשעה חודשים, tish'ah chodashim, for nine months, שנאמר, she-ne'emar, לכן יתנם
עד עת יולדה ילדה, lachein yitnem ad eit yoledah yaladah, therefore he
will give them until the time that the woman giving birth will
give birth, ויתר אחיו ישובון על בני ישראל, ve-yeter achiv yeshuvun al
Bnei Yisrael, and the remnant of the brothers will return. So how
long does it take to give birth? Nine months. So only when
they have dominion over the entire world for nine months, only then
will there be a משיח. Mashiach. Okay, we with that we end
the אגדתא Agadata and return to the discussion of the משנה. Mishnah.
Yes.
These, these are mostly relatively early אמוראים Amoraim in בבל, Bavel, so
they would not have known at this time that the Roman empire
was in the process of falling apart internally.
Okay, so that's why they could be having this discussion about whether
Rome will, will conquer the world.
But it's interesting that they're, they're actually, they're living under Persian rule
and they're even discussing the fact that Persia might be,
might fall to Rome or vice
versa. Right. Good point to, right, which side are they, from which
perspective are they looking. Okay, back to the משנה. Mishnah. תנו רבנן,
Tanu Rabbanan, כל הלשכות שהיו במקדש לא היה להן מזוזה. kol ha-lishkot
she-hayu ba-mikdash lo hayah lahen mezuzah. All the, all the rooms that
they, the chambers in the מקדש... Mikdash... have a מזוזה, mezuzah, חוץ
מלשכת פרהדרין, chutz milishkat parhedrin, except for this chamber, שהיתה בה בית
דירה לכהן גדול, shehayta bah beit dirah lekohen gadol, that's where the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would live, so that had a
מזוזה. mezuzah. אמר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda, said Rabbi Yehuda, and
do you
mean like sleeping or does living mean no?
Sleeping, yes. We've been discussing that before, how could he sleep in
it, would he eat there?
No, let's not get into that right now, let's assume he fully
lives there, I'm not going to discuss dividing a place you sleep
and you eat. Okay, he fully lives there. אמר רבי יהודה, Amar
Rabbi Yehuda, but were there not many chambers in the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash that had a בית דירה? beit dirah? There were a
number of chambers in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash that people lived
in, like the כהנים Kohanim would live, you know, they sleep in
if they were out on the watch of the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and they didn't have a מזוזה, mezuzah, אלא
לשכת פרהדרין. ela Lishkat Parhedrin. So it was, so now, so rather,
it was, so meaning the fact that you live in a room
in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash does not obligated it in a
מזוזה. mezuzah. Why not? We'll have to see. Meaning, it is true,
for example, שולס shuls don't need a מזוזה mezuzah because people don't
live in them, they don't sleep and eat in them. But if
they're actually there are rooms, I mean we put it up for
pro-termina but it doesn't technically require it. But if people actually do
live and sleep in the, you know, in the שול, shul, then
it would require. So okay, the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash by itself
wouldn't require a מזוזה, mezuzah, but why would a room not? But
that's רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's argument. I mean, he doesn't say why,
but he gives evidence. He says, look, there were many chambers that
people slept in, did not have a מזוזה. mezuzah. For whatever reason,
the rooms in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash even if they're lived
in don't require מזוזה. mezuzah. But he doesn't disagree about לשכת פרהדרין.
Lishkat Parhedrin. אלא לשכת פרהדרין גזירה היתה. ela Lishkat Parhedrin gzeira hayta.
By לשכת פרהדרין, Lishkat Parhedrin, it was not that it was really
obligated in a מזוזה, mezuzah, it was a גזירה. gzeira. And what
was the גזירה? gzeira? So we'll see that in a minute. The
גמרא Gemara is going to
say... but if people live in the other rooms, it doesn't have
a מזוזה. mezuzah. So the גמרא Gemara is gonna say... same person.
Right, so a, you could just say it's a lot of focus
on the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol for seven days straight, right? We'll
see other reasons the גמרא Gemara will say, but he says in
principle, chambers in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, even lived in, do
not require a מזוזה, mezuzah, and we'll see why. You should note
by the way that in the תוספתא, Tosefta, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says the exact opposite. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says there are a
couple, many rooms in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash that people live
in and they all have a מזוזה. mezuzah. Okay, so the תוספתא
Tosefta is the exact reverse of this quote here of רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. But this source says, in principle, no מזוזה, mezuzah, but
לשכת פרהדרין Lishkat Parhedrin was a גזירה. gzeira. So מאי טעמא דרבי
יהודה, Mai Ta'ama deRabbi Yehuda, what's the reason of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda that there's no need for a מזוזה mezuzah in the rooms
in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash even if they're lived in? So
אמר רבה קסבר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbah kasavar Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda holds כל בית שאינו עשוי לימות החמה ולימות הגשמים, kol
bayit she'eino asui limot hachama ulimot hageshamim, any place that's not made
for living throughout the year, אינו בית, eino bayit, the winter and
the summer. Okay, because... so therefore whatever rooms that people slept in,
you know, כהן גדול Kohen Gadol a week, other people a few
days, nobody lives in there
year round. איתיביה אביי, Etvei Abaye, אביי Abaye asks on this, וּכְתִיב,
vakativ, does it not say והכיתי בית החרף על בית הקיץ, vehikeiti
beit hachoref al beit hakayitz, I will destroy the winter house against
the summer house? So you see it's called a בית. bayit. So
אמר ליה, amar lei, בית חרף ובית קיץ איקרי, beit choref ubeit
kayitz ikri, it's called a winter house or summer house, בית סתם
לא איקרי, bayit stam lo ikri, but סתם stam house it's not
called, so it doesn't have the status of בית. bayit. I just
have to say I was watching the other day, you know how
Rahm Emanuel got really angry because the new World Trade Center is
tallest building now, there was an official ruling or whatever, so he
was talking, anyway he got up and talking and then so on
the news they were talking about well Chicago still better than New
York because like you know Chicago style pizza, the pan pizza is
so much better than New York
pizza, so Jon Stewart had a whole little thing
where first he goes on this rant against pan pizza and then
he says, and you know what? He says, you call your stuff
pan pizza, Chicago style pizza, then takes a slice of pizza he
says, you know what this is? Pizza.
So anyway that's basically the point. Okay, it could be called a
winter house or summer house. House it isn't if it needs a
modifier, it's not the real thing. So the גמרא Gemara says, so
that's the first answer. But the גמרא Gemara says, בית סתם לא
איקרי. bayit stam lo ikri. So איתיביה אביי, etvei Abaye, so אביי
Abaye asked on this, you really think that that's true, that you
know just because it's a few days it doesn't require a מזוזה?
mezuzah? Look, I'll show you actually what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says.
סוכת החג בחג, Sukkat HeChag beChag, what's the story with your סוכה
sukkah during סוכות? Sukkot? Does it need a מזוזה? mezuzah? רבי יהודה
מחייב, Rabbi Yehuda mechayiv, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would have you put
up a מזוזה mezuzah in your סוכה, sukkah, וחכמים פוטרין, veChachamim potrin,
and the חכמים Chachamim exempt. So here it's the opposite, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is more demanding of a מזוזה. mezuzah. Which fits with
the תוספתא, Tosefta, but not with our version. Okay, so רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is more demanding. ותניא עלה, Vetanya ala, and we taught
on a ברייתא Baraita on it, רבי יהודה מחייב בעירוב, Rabbi Yehuda
mechayiv be'eruv, he would demand that you have an עירוב, eruv, meaning
if it opens up into a courtyard it would have to participate
in the עירוב, eruv, וּבִמְזוּזָה, u'vemezuzah, it needs a מזוזה, mezuzah, he
really treats it like a house, וּבְמַעֲשֵׂר, u'vema'aser, and with מעשר, ma'aser,
meaning if you bring grain into the house, once you bring it
into the house it's obligated in מעשר, ma'aser, but it has to
be something that has the status of a house. So you see
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda really considers it a
house. Not have the same approach about the chambers in the בית
המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
Just a clarification. You tell me when the תבואה Tevuah is still
growing in the field?
Not only growing, when it's harvested and in the bundles, it's only
rabbinically חייב Chayav in מעשר. Maaser. It has to be brought in—normally
you don't bring it into the house, you bring it into the
barn.
Into the barn—once it comes inside of
your—right, exactly, it's ראיית פני הבית. Reeias Pnei Habayis. Only then is
it biblically obligated, okay? Or is it considered טבל Tevel if you
eat it without taking it? You know, we could speak about there's
sort of being a חיוב Chiyuv but it's not yet status of
טבל. Tevel. Anyway, וכי תימא מדרבנן, V'chi Teima Miderabbanan, so maybe the
reason he requires, gives סוכות Sukkos this status is all rabbinic? Okay,
so בשלמא, Bishlama, the גמרא Gemara says it can't be, it's gotta
be biblical. בשלמא עירוב מזוזה איכא למימר מדרבנן—to Bishlama Eruv Mezuzah Ika
L'meimar Miderabbanan require to do an עירוב, Eruv, to require to put
up a מזוזה, Mezuzah, that you could say is rabbinic. אלא מעשר,
Ella Maaser, to require מעשר Maaser to be taken when it's brought
into such a place, that would not be rabbinic. מי איכא למימר
מדרבנן? Mika L'meimar Miderabbanan? How could you say it's rabbinic? We're gonna
finish
the דף Daf today, okay? דדלמא אתי לאפרושי מן החיוב על הפטור
ומן הפטור לחיוב—we D'dilma Ati L'afroshei Min Hachiyuv Al Hapatour Umin Hapatour
L'chiyuv would not make something only rabbinically obligated in תרומות ומעשרות Trumos
U'maasros because people will think it's biblically obligated and they'll come to
take from this grain which is biblically exempt on grain that's biblically
obligated, or the reverse. So therefore, we would never make it something
rabbinically obligated in תרומות ומעשרות. Trumos U'maasros. Of course that's absurd, and
that's one of the big תוספות Tosfos that shorten the דף Daf
for us is there's plenty of times we have rabbinic obligations of
תרומות ומעשרות. Trumos U'maasros. So number one is if they're types of
species, like a type of food that's different, you know, certain types—I
don't know, let's say vegetables—the whole obligation of תרומות ומעשרות Trumos U'maasros
is rabbinic. Fine, but you don't have to be concerned that you'll
take from exempt on obligated because you don't take from vegetables on
wheat, right? So there's no problem if we make an obligation of
a category of food as rabbinic, you won't cross categories. But תוספות
Tosfos says there are also times where we make wheat
that's only—that's for some reason is not biblically obligated—we make it rabbinically
obligated. Why are we concerned here and not there? His basic short
answer is that you know some of those differences are more obvious.
This difference will easily be confused. They see a guy living in
a hut, they see him bringing wheat into it, you know, it's
very easy to assume—there's nothing obvious that marks it as only rabbinically
obligated. So therefore, we would never make that rabbinically obligated because then
it will lead to you mixing up rabbinic and biblical and lead
to you separating תרומות ומעשרות Trumos U'maasros from this wheat to exempt
other wheat, and that won't work because one is rabbinic and the
other is biblical.
Can I say something really basic? All the time though, something that
the רבנן Rabbanan more מחמיר Machmir than the דאורייתא. D'oraisa. What am
I missing?
I'm not sure. You mean what's stopping us from making things דרבנן?
Derabbanan? Yeah, that's what I said a minute ago. תוספות Tosfos points
out, תוספות—so Tosfos do you understand what the problem is having grain
that's only rabbinically obligated, what it might lead to? If this grain
here is biblically obligated and this is rabbinically obligated, right? And I
say I am מפריש Mafresh my תרומות ומעשרות Trumos U'maasros from this
grain for all of this—which I can do, right—then I'll think that
I can eat this grain. But from the Torah's perspective, it wasn't
an actual act of הפרשה, Hafrasha, and this grain remains טבל. Tevel.
So that's the concern. תוספות—so Tosfos then we should always be concerned,
and the basic answer is there's nothing that clearly demarks this grain
as different than that grain. And here we would never make it
rabbinically obligated because it could easily lead to that scenario.
Right, you wouldn't think that you're taking מעשר Maaser on a wheat
if you were מפריש מעשר Mafresh Maaser from vegetables.
Right, exactly. So it cannot be rabbinic, it's got to be biblical.
So now we've got that רב יהודה Reb Yehuda biblically obligates a
סוכה Sukkah in מזוזה. Mezuzah. So why is he having a problem
with the rooms in the
בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? אלא אמר אביי, Ella Amar Abaye, בשבעה—during Bishiva
the seven days, okay, of סוכות Sukkos or the seven days of
the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. But let's say the seven days of
סוכות. Sukkos. One of the other reasons this דף Daf is so
long—short—is because it's a huge second תוספות, Tosfos, sort of tries to
figure—you know, has the whole argument on רש"י Rashi how to read
this גמרא. Gemara. So I'm going to basically read it תוספות's Tosfos
way. Okay, בשבעה, Bishiva, during the seven days
somebody is living there, whether the seven days of סוכות—the Sukkos way
תוספות Tosfos reads
this—or the... Okay, everybody would agree it's biblically. כי פליגי בשאר ימות
השנה. Ki piligi be-sh'ar yemos hashanah.
Now the debate about whether לשכת פרהדרין Lishkas Parhedrin was biblically obligated
in a מזוזה mezuzah or not, you know, that is rabbinic. That
is about the rest
of the year. רבנן סברי לא גזרינן Rabbanan savri lo gazrinan בשאר
ימות השנה אטו שבעה, be-sh'ar yemos hashanah atu shiva, we do not
make a גזירה, gzaira, the rest of the year will lead to
those seven days, ורבי יהודה סבר גזרינן, ve-Rabbi Yehuda savar gazrinan, we
do. So what he says that means is the following: he says
that according to the Rabbis, hold on, let me just give me
one
second. One minute.
One
minute.
Okay, so fine. So the way תוספות Tosfos reads this is, let
me see if I can get this right. The way תוספות Tosfos
reads this is the following: is that according to the Rabbis, the
Rabbis only apply the biblical rule. So they say that when somebody
is living in the לשכת פרהדרין, Lishkas Parhedrin, okay, then they are,
then it's חייב chayav in a מזוזה. mezuzah. What? Isn't that the
two... תוספות. Tosfos.
Yeah,
so the גמרא's Gemara going to challenge that in a minute, okay.
So when somebody is living it's חייב chayav in a מזוזה. mezuzah.
The whole debate is when people aren't living there, so which would
be the סוכה Sukkah on the rest of the year, the לשכת
פרהדרין Lishkas Parhedrin in the rest of the year, the other
לשכאות, lishkaot, those would be the debate. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and the רבנן Rabbanan say לא גזרינן lo gazrinan that we don't
obligate them when they're not really obligated. רבי יהודה סבר גזרינן. Rabbi
Yehuda savar gazrinan. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds we make a
גזירה gzaira and therefore we rabbinically mandate that there be a מזוזה
mezuzah even when the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol isn't living in the
לשכת פרהדרין Lishkas Parhedrin and even in, you know, I'm getting this...
was there a סוכה ישנה? Sukkah yeshana?
Hold on one minute. I'm just one minute. I'm sorry, I'm sorry,
this is very... it's just getting confused. Hold on a second.
Okay,
I'm getting this confused. You know what? I mean, okay, I'll try
one more time and if not we'll go on because the גמרא,
Gemara, it's about to get very much easier in the next statement.
I'll try one more time. The way תוספות Tosfos reads this is
that רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the, you know
what? I'm going to just get to the next line. Okay, so
somehow the גמרא Gemara makes an argument that they're only arguing on
the rest of the year about the status of the לשכה lishka
and the status of the סוכה Sukkah and they're only arguing about
the rest of the year, everybody agrees that during the חג chag
it is דאורייתא. de-oraisa.
So let's see how the גמרא Gemara rejects that, okay. Exactly how
it imagined that would work out is complicated, but let's see how
the גמרא Gemara rejects that. אמר ליה רבא, Amlei Rava, so the
understanding why it rejects it is easy and this is what Michael
was saying, וסוכת החג בחג קתני. Ve-Sukkas hachag be-chag katani. You can't
say that everybody agrees during סוכות Sukkos that it's obligated. The whole
debate of the רבנן Rabbanan and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is on
סוכות. Sukkos. It's explicit whether it needs a מזוזה mezuzah or not.
אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, now this is much clearer. בשאר
ימות השנה כולי עלמא לא פליגי דפטורה. Be-sh'ar yemos hashanah kulei alma
lo peligi de-petura. The rest of the year everybody agrees it's exempt.
Nobody's living in it. כי פליגי בשבעה. Ki peligi be-shiva.
The debate is when it's being lived in. וסוכה טעמא לחוד ולשכה
טעמא לחוד. Ve-Sukkah taima le-chud ve-lishka taima le-chud. And each one by
the way, how come everybody is reversing their position? רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is lenient in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and strict by
the סוכה. Sukkah. The רבנן Rabbanan are reversed. So it says each
one has its own separate issue. Let's take a look. סוכה טעמא
לחוד, Sukkah taima le-chud, סוכה Sukkah is one debate. רבי יהודה לטעמיה
דאמר סוכה דירת קבע בעינן. Rabbi Yehuda le-taimei de-amar Sukkah diras keva
ba'inan. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda goes according to his reasoning in the
beginning of סוכות. Sukkos. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says a סוכה Sukkah
can be a hundred feet high because he thinks that a סוכה
Sukkah can be and maybe has to be a permanent dwelling. So
if it is considered to be a permanent dwelling, it's a real
dwelling, it's obligated in a מזוזה. mezuzah. ומחייב במזוזה. Um'chayiva bimezuzah. ורבנן
לטעמייהו, Ve-Rabbanan le-taimeihu, the Rabbis go according to
their... So that debate is completely about the status of סוכה. sukkah.
סוכה sukkah is this flimsy thing, it's only made for a week.
Forget a house I only live in in the summer, but it
lasts throughout the year. A סוכה sukkah is made for a week
to be taken down. So the Rabbis say logically it's not a
house. Rabbi יהודה Yehuda says during that week, that becomes your house
and it has the status of a דירת קבע diras keva for
that week. So that's a debate, doesn't matter how you construct it.
Halachically, is that considered to be a temporary dwelling or no, the
idea of סוכות Sukkos is the temporary dwelling becomes my house? Is
it considered to be a דירת עראי diras arai or דירת קבע?
diras keva? It's only made for seven days. This would not apply
to anything other than a סוכה sukkah on סוכות. Sukkos. If I
made a little hut in my backyard for a week, everybody would
agree it's exempt. The question is the status of it as a
סוכה. sukkah. That's that debate. Okay, the לשכה lishka in the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Now the לשכה lishka in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash has its own reasoning. רבנן סברי דירה בעל כרחה שמיה דירה.
Rabbanan savri dira be'al korcha shemeih dira. This is what it's about.
Because you have to live there in a permanent structure, but you're
forced to live there. It's like a jail. If I'm in jail,
God forbid, do I say I need my religious needs, I have
a right to have them met, I need a מזוזה mezuzah on
my door on the jail? Okay. So well, you don't really anyway
they can move you around, you don't really have any בעלות ba'alus
over the place. But if you are forced to live there, is
it considered to be a בית דירה? beis dira? Part of living
means that you're not a prisoner, that you are empowered. So is
that considered to be a דירה? dira? רבנן סברי דירה בעל כרחה
שמיה דירה Rabbanan savri dira be'al korcha shemeih dira and therefore it's
obligated in a מזוזה. mezuzah. And that's why they say it was
not rabbinic, it was biblically obligated. רבי יהודה סבר דירה בעל כרחה
לא שמיה דירה. Rabbi Yehuda savar dira be'al korcha lo shemeih dira.
It's not. No place in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is anybody
living out of a choice. If anybody is living in any room,
they're forced to live there. And therefore there's no obligation in a
מזוזה. mezuzah. Now what's his גזירה? gezeirah? Why do they have it
therefore in the לשכת פרהדרין Lishkas Parhedrin according to him as a
גזירה? gezeirah? What's the גזירה? gezeirah? ומדרבנן הוא דתיקנו לה, u'miderabbanan hu
detiknu lah, it was all rabbinic, שלא יאמרו כהן גדול חבוש בבית
האסורים. shelo yomru Kohen Gadol chavush be'veis ha'asurim. So they shouldn't say
exactly for the reason it's I've listened to it, but it's consistent.
The reason he doesn't consider it to be a בית דירה beis
dira is because you are imprisoned there. So he views it as
being imprisoned, as it were, I'm making it as an extreme, and
therefore exempt from a מזוזה. mezuzah. And it's because he views it
as that that he has to obligate you in a מזוזה mezuzah
so you don't view it that way. So anyway, so they both
agree that the point of מזוזה mezuzah shows you're living there and
you're not imprisoned. But the Rabbis start by saying you're living there
and you're biblically obligated. Rabbi יהודה Yehuda starts by saying you're somewhat
imprisoned there and you're not biblically obligated, but we're going to make
a מזוזה mezuzah to make it look like you're not. Okay, so
we'll see more about this tomorrow.